Guide to the Boyd Ellsworth Payton Papers, 1929-1977 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Boyd Ellsworth Payton papers 1929-1977 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Payton, Boyd E.
1,831 Items
Labor leader from Willingboro (Burlington Co.), N.J.
Papers concerning the career of Boyd Ellsworth Payton, International Vice President of the Textile Workers Union of America. The papers concern three major aspects of Payton's career: the Harriet-Henderson Cotton Mills strike (1958-1961); his incarceration and writing of the book, Scapegoat; and finally his experiences after being released from prison. Included are genealogical materials, correspondence, legal papers, addresses and writings, miscellaneous items, radio scripts, pictures, and a draft of Scapegoat, entitled Prejudice + Politics = Prison. Other papers include items on the poll tax in the South, as well as pamphlets relating to labor unions and the South, the poll tax, and strikes. Clippings deal principally with the American Federation of Labor (AFL), AFL publicity, South Carolina Federation of Labor Convention, United Textile Workers of America convention, communists, and the Bessemer City strike. A 1929 scrapbook houses clippings pertaining to the southern textile strike in that year, and a 1946 scrapbook contains information on the Danville (Va.) Citizens' Committee, a group organized to fight inflation and high prices in Danville. Formerly part of the Labor Archives Collection. Original box numbers have been retained.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Boyd Ellsworth Payton Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1977.
Collection Overview
Papers date from 1929 to 1977 and concern the career of Boyd Ellsworth Payton, International Vice President of the Textile Workers Union of America. The papers concern three major aspects of Payton's career: the Harriet-Henderson Cotton Mills strike (1958-1961); his incarceration in prison and writing of the book, Scapegoat; and finally his experiences after being released from jail. Included are genealogical materials, correspondence, legal papers, addresses and writings, miscellaneous items, radio scripts, pictures, and a draft of Scapegoat, entitled Prejudice + Politics = Prison. Other papers include items on the poll tax in the South, as well as pamphlets relating to labor unions and the South, the poll tax, and strikes. Clippings deal principally with the American Federation of Labor (AFL), AFL publicity, South Carolina Federation of Labor Convention, United Textile Workers of America convention, communists, and the Bessemer City strike. A 1929 scrapbook houses clippings pertaining to the southern textile strike in that year, and a 1946 scrapbook contains information on the Danville (Va.) Citizens' Committee, a group organized to fight inflation and high prices in Danville. One box of material was formerly part of the Labor Archives Collection. Original box number has been retained.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Payton, Boyd E., 1908-1984
American Federation of Labor
Danville Citizens' Committee (Danville, Va.)
South Carolina State Federation of Labor
United Textile Workers of America
Textile Workers Union of America
Henderson Cotton Mills (Henderson, N.C.)
Consumer cooperatives -- Virginia -- Danville
Poll tax -- Southern States
Strikes and lockouts -- Textile industry -- North Carolina
Textile Workers' Strike, Gastonia, N.C., 1929
Labor unions and communism -- United States
Labor unions -- Southern States
Textile workers -- Labor unions
Textile Workers' Strike, Henderson, N.C., 1958-1961
Textile industry -- North Carolina
Related Material
A substantial collection of Boyd E. Payton's papers are also held by the University of North Carolina, Charlotte Special Collections. See the online finding aid for more details.
Contents of Collection
- Addresses and Writings Series, 1958-1970 and undated, (3 boxes)
  - Addresses and Writings (Box 1)
    - 1958-1970
    - Undated (Box 5)
  - Radio Scripts (Box 7)
- Correspondence Series, 1950-1975, (2 boxes)
  - 1950-1963 (Box 3)
  - 1964-1975 (Box 6)
- Legal Papers Series, 1945-1970 and undated, (2 boxes)
  - 1945-1970 (Box 6)
  - Undated (Box 1)
- Printed Material Series, 1950-1976, (3 boxes)
  - Printed Material (Box 2)
  - Clippings
    - 1963-1976
    - 1950-1960 (Box 8)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Series, (4 boxes)
  - Genealogy (Box 3)
  - Unprocessed material (Box 4)
  - Miscellany
  - Radio scripts, Pictures (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 10)
- Additional Papers, (1 box)
  - Additional papers (Box 326)
    Unprocessed and undescribed. Formerly part of the Labor Archives Collections. See catalog record for Boyd Ellsworth Payton Papers for location.
- Oversize Materials
  - The South, poll tax broadside (Opaperfolder OF1)